Mss.B.G96 Mss.B.G96
American Philosophical Society
John Thomas Gulick papers, 1853-1898
Mss.B.G96
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
This collection includes correspondence on natural history and evolution, and especially on his collection and study of shells from Japan and the Pacific islands. Principal correspondents include Louis Agassiz, Charles Robert Darwin, Sir William Henry Flower, Alpheus Hyatt, George Newbold Lawrence, George J. Romanes, Alfred R. Wallace, and the Linnean Society of London.
Ca. 100 items.
Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gulick, Addison. See in-house shelf list for additional dates and numbers.
Custodial History note
Presented by Addison Gulick, 1960-1961.
General note
Many of the letters were printed in Addison Gulick, "Evolutionist and Missionary: John Thomas Gulick, Portrayed Through Documents and Discussions" (Chicago, 1932).
Biographical/Historical note
John Thomas Gulick (1832-1923) was born at Waimea, Kauai, Hawaii. The son of Rev. Peter Johnson and Fanny Hinckley (Thomas) Gulick, early American missionaries to Hawaii, he travelled extensively as a missionary and contributed to the early development of evolutionary science, beginning with his study of Hawaiian land snails.
Gulick studied at Punahou Academy in Honolulu and the preparatory department of the University of the City of New York. After a short time in California, where he worked as a miner (1849-1850) he graduated from Williams College in 1859 and the Union Theological Seminary in 1861. In 1862 he travelled to Japan, supporting himself by teaching and photography which trying to convince the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions to begin work in the area. From 1864 to 1899 he worked as a Board missionary in various locations, including Peking and Kalgan in China and Kobe and Osaka in Japan. Returning to the United States in 1900, he studied problems related to evolution at Oberlin, Ohio.
Gulick maintained that perfect harmony is possible between science and religion, and that the two major themes of his life – missionary work and evolutionary biology – were perfectly compatible. His son and biographer notes: “The scientist’s psychology would be but half told without the portrayal of the almost mystical religious awe with which great scientific truths were approached. And the development … of a carefully thought philosophy of life would be unaccounted for without an exposition of the scientific concepts that gave an impetus to changing stand-points toward religion and the problems of human conduct. To a singular degree the diversity of Gulick’s achievements sprang out of a unity of personal character and purpose.”
Gulick was twice married. His first wife, Emily de la Cour, died in 1874. With his second wife, Frances A. Stevens, he had two children, Addison and Louise. In 1906 Gulick returned to Hawaii to devote himself to the study of social problems. He died there in 1923, at the age of ninety-one.
Scope and Contents note
The correspondence in this collection represent primarily one facet of Gulick’s life, that of evolutionary theorist and natural philosopher. The correspondence deal with his collection of shells collected in Hawaii, publications on evolution, and his running debate with Alfred Russel Wallace.
The correspondence are separated into three series. Series one is general correspondence, and represents a cross-section of all of the above themes. Series two is composed of nineteen letters between Gulick and the prominent American zoologist and paleontologist Alpheus Hyatt (1838-1902). The letters are primarily concerned with natural history in general, and specifically with details of Gulicks collections of Hawaiian shells and publications related to them. Series three is composed of 60 letters, the majority of which are between Gulick and the English evolutionary theorist George John Romanes (1848-1894), and refer mostly to evolutionary debate between Gulick and Alfred Russel Wallace, publications on evolution and Gulick’s collection of Hawaiian shells.
Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902; Lawrence, George N.(George Newbold),1806-1895.; Linnean Society of London.; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913; Evolution.; Mollusks -- Japan.; Natural history.; Shells -- Japan.
- Series One: General Correspondence, 1853-1889; B G96; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence in series one is the most varied, and deal with Gulick’s efforts to find a home for his collection of shells and his publications and presentations with the Linnean Society. Of particular interest are three letters with Charles Darwin, the original of which are in the Darwin papers (B D25).
  D. 19 items. Various sizes. Presented by Addison Gulick; July 1960.
  - The distribution of plants and animals, April 7, 1853; B G96; 10x8; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.D. 11p.,end. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence; 1853-1888.) "Read before the Punahou Debating Society April 7, 1853" Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary, J.T.Gulick,pp.114-119.
  - Letter to [John Thomas Gulick], Sept. 3, 1872; B G96; 7x4-1/2; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913
    A.L.S. 2p. (see J.T.Gullick. Correspondence...: 1853-1888.) Asks for map to accompany his paper, with Wallace will present for publication to the Linnean Society. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary, p.235.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, New York, Oct. 23, 1872; B G96; 8x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correpondence...; 1853-1888.) Concerning geographic distribution and the Darwinian theory. Printed: A. Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary, p.237.
  - Letter to Charles [Robert] Darwin, July 27, 1872; B G96 no. 421; 7x4-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence...; 1853-1888.) Asks to meet him and discuss the distribution of species of Hawaiian mollusks. Printed: A.Gulick.Evolutionist and Missionary,J.T.Gulick. pp.233.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, July 28, [1872]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Photo. 4p. and add. For original, see Darwin papers (B D25)
  - Letter t o John T. Gulick, August 8, [1872]; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
    Photo. 4p. add. For original, see Darwin papers (B D25)
  - Description of a collection of Sandwich Island land shells which Prof.Agassiz had engaged to purchase shortly before his death, 1874; B G96; 10-1/2x8; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    [ca.]. A.D.S. 6p. (see Gulick papers.)
  - Letter to John [T. Gulick], June 6, 1887; B G96; 8x5; Gulick, Edward Leeds, 1862-1931
    Hanover, N. H., A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Gulick papers.) Concerning the disposition of his shells.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, London, May 22, 1888; B G96; 8x5; Linnean Society of London
    London, A.L.S.: W. Percy Sladen. 2p.and end.and receipt for £15.0.0 (see Gulick papers.) Concerning his paper on divergent evolution.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, London, July 12, 1888; B G96; 9x7-1/2; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899
    London, L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Gulick papers.) Must decline the purchase of his shells
  - Letter to Prof. [Sir William Henry] Flower, July 13, 1888; B G96; 8x6-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.L.S. 12p. Draft of letter, in pencil (see Gulick papers.) Concerning the final disposition of his shell collection.
  - Letter to [Henri] de Varigny, Sept. 17, 1888; B G96; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. Draft, in pencil. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence...; 1853-1888.) Forwards paper on evolution and asks for comments on it.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, Sept. 27, 1888; B G96; 7x4-1/2; Dallinger, W. H. (William Henry), 1842-1909
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Gulick papers.) Can see him next Friday.
  - Letter to [John T. Gulick], Sept. 28, 1888; B G96; 7x4-1/2; MacAlister, Donald, 1854-1934
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. (see Gulick papers.) Thanks him for his paper and believes his solution correct.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Oct. 5, 1888; B G96; 8x5; Lawrence, George N. (George Newbold), 1806-1895
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. (see Gulick papers) Asks what to do with the birds left with him. Some were presented to the American museum of natural history. On same sheet is: Gulick to Lawrence; June 14, 1889.
  - Letter to [George N.] Lawrence, June 14, 1889; B G96; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Medina, A.L. 2p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) His brother presents birds to American museum of natural history. Hopes it will purchase his collection of shells. On same sheet as: Lawrence to Gulick; Oct. 5,1888.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, June 20, 1889; B G96; 7x4-1/2; Lawrence, George N. (George Newbold), 1806-1895
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. (see Gulick papers.) Thanks for the birds for the American museum of natural history. Inquires of his collection of shells.
  - Suggestions concerning the mounting of the geographical collection of land shells from the Island of Oahu, Nov., 1889; B G96; 8-1/4x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.D. 8p. In pencil. Draft. (see Gulick papers.)
  - Letter to Prof. [Sir William Henry] Flower., Undated; B G96; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.L.S. 2p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Concerning the arrangement of land shells from Oahu to show divergent evolution.
  - Memoranda pertaining to shells., Undated; B G96; 4x7-1/4 and 3-1/2x5-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.D. 2 items. (see Gulick papers.)
- Series Two: Correspondence with Alpheus Hyatt, 1890-1898; B G96.h; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
  Correspondence between Gulick and the prominent American zoologist and paleontologist Alpheus Hyatt (1838-1902), primarily concerned with natural history in general, and specifically with details of Gulicks collections of Hawaiian shells and publications related to them.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, March 15, 1890; B G96.h; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Recommends he publish a major work on Hawaiian mollusks. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.321-322.
  - Letter to [John Thomas] Gulick, Oct. 31, 1896; B G96.h; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston Typed L.S. 5p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Believes the Boston society of natural history would purchase his collection of shells, but wants a definite statement of the sale price.
  - Letter to John [Thomas] Gulick, Osaka, Japan, Jan. 5, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L. 1p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Asks for statement of cost of his collections of shells.
  - Memorandum of letter sent to Alpheus Hyatt, Feb. 24, 1897; B G96.h; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.D. 1p. In pencil. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) States the price he asks for his collections of shells.
  - Letter to John [Thomas] Gulick, Osaka, Japan, March 2, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L. 1p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt) Inquires for cost of his collection of shells.
  - Letter to John [Thomas] Gulick, Osaka, Japan, March 18, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 1p.and add., end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning the distribution of shells in Hawaii. Will purchase his collection.
  - Letter to John [Thomas] Gulick, Osaka, Japan, March 25, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L. 1p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt) Is lending some of his collection and wishes to be absolved of responsibility.
  - Letter to [Alpheus] Hyatt, April 23, 1897; B G96.h; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, Japan, A.L.S. 3p. Copy. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning his sets of shells and price asked.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, Osaka, Japan, April 26, [1897?]; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 2p.and add. Incomplete. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning the distribution of shells in Hawaii.
  - Letter to [Alpheus] Hyatt, April 30, 1897; B G96.h; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, Typed L. 3p. Copy. 11c8-1/2 (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning his collection of shells and their sources in Hawaii.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, Osaka, Japan, May 13, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Will try to arrange for his collection of Hawaiian shells to come into the country duty free.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, May 26, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Osaka, Japan, Boston, Typed L.S. 4p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning his collection of Hawaiian shells and the publication of them.
  - Letter to[Alpheus] Hyatt, June 5, 1897; B G96.h; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, Japan, A.L. 8p. In pencil. Draft. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt) Concerning the shipment of his collection of shells.
  - Letter to [Alpheus] Hyatt, June 15, 1897; B G96.h; 11x8-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, Japan, Typed L. 4p. Copy. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning the distribution of shells in Hawaii.
  - Letter to [Alpheus] Hyatt, June 18, 1897; B G96.h; 11x8-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Typed L. 3p. Copy. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning mollusks in Hawaii.
  - Notes sent to [Alpheus] Hyatt, Nov., 1897; B G96.h; 11x8-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Typed D. 8p. Copy. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning mollusks in Hawaii.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, Osaka,Japan, Dec. 11, 1897; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 4p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning mollusks in Hawaii.
  - Memorandum of correspondence with Alpheus Hyatt, 1897-1899; B G96.h; 11x8-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Typed D. 1p. Copy. (see J. T. Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt)
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, Osaka, Japan, Dec. 27, 1898; B G96.h; 8-1/2x5-1/4; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902
    Boston, Typed L.S. 4p.and add.,end. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Hyatt.) Concerning shells in Hawaii.
- Series Three: Correspondence with George John Romanes, 1887-1893; B G96.r; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
  Correspondence between Gulick and the English evolutionary theorist George John Romanes (1848-1894), refering mostly to evolutionary debate between Gulick and Alfred Russel Wallace, publications on evolution and Gulick’s collection of Hawaiian shells.
  Also included in this series is a bound volume containing transcripts of the correspondence between Gulick and Romanes.
  D. 60 items. Various sizes. Presented by Addison Gulick; June 1960. Table of contents available.
  - Correspondence with George John Romanes, etc., 1872-1893; B G96.r.1; 11x8-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Typescript. 1 vol.bound of 195p. Printed (in large part): Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary. Originals in: B:G96.r. Presented by Addison Gulick; Jan. 1961.
  - Letter to [John T. Gulick], Oct. 19, 1887; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning his paper which Wallace is forwarding to the Linnean society for possible publication. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionst and missionary...; pp.404-405.
  - Letter to [John T. Gulick], Jan. 16, 1888; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Recommended to the Linnean Society that his paper on evolution be published. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.405-406.
  - Letter to the secretary of the Linnean society of London, April 10, 1888; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Rome, A.L. 4p. Draft. In pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Concerning the publication of his article: "Divergent Evolution through Cumulative Segregation". Refers to Wallace.
  - Letter to G[eorge] J[ohn] Romanes, London, April 28, 1888; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Genoa, A.L.S. 4p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Printed in part: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; p.406.
  - Letter to G. J. [John T.] Gulick, London, July 22, [1888]; B G96.r; 5-1/2x3-3/4; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S.on postal card. 1p.and add. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning his publications. Printed: A. Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; p.407.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, London, Aug. 26, [1888]; B G96.r; 4-3/4x3; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S.on postal card. 1p.and add. (see J.T.Gulick Correspondence with Romanes.) Asks to borrow shells from Hawaii.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Aug. 26, 1888; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 2p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Suggests he send a copy of his paper on evolution to Henri de Varigny. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; 407-408.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Aug. 31, 1888; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.L.S. 6p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Printed in part: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.408-409.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Sept. 2, 1888; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Thanks for the loan of his shells. Hopes he can sell his collection in England. Printed in part: A.Gulick.Evolutionist and missionary...; 409-410
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Oct. 12, 1888; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Makes suggestions for his reply to Wallace on evolution. Refers to Huxley.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Oct. 27, 1888; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Boston, A.L. 8p. Draft. In pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Printed (almost completely): Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.410-411.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Oct. 29, 1888; B G96.r; 8x6-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    A.L.S. 3p. Draft. In pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Concerning shipment and responsibility of his shells. Encloses suggested receipt.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Dec. 12, 1888; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning the dispute with Wallace. Concerning his ideas on evolution. Shells. Printed: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.411-412.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Dec. 29, 1888; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Boston, A.L. 17p. Draft. Partly in pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Printed (in large part): Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.412-415.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, May 21, 1889; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning Wallace and natural selection. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionst and missionary...; pp.416-417.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Sept. 30, 1889; B G96.r; 6x4; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning natural selection. Concerning Wallace and Darwinism. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...;p.417.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Oct. 10, 1889; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S.. 4p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes. Prefers no controversy with Wallace. Thinks that a book on evolution would be of much greater importane, based on his study of shells. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; p.417.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T[homas] Gulick, Osaka, Nov. 21, 1889; B G96.r; 10x7; Swett, Charles E
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Carbon copy. (see Gulick papers.) Delivered shells to Dr. Hyatt.
  - Letter to John T. Gulick, Osaka, Dec. 12, 1889; B G96.r; 9-1/2x6; Swett, Charles E
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Gulick papers.) Be some delay for payment for shells from Hyatt.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Dec. 19, 1889; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 2p. Draft. In pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Printed in part: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; p.419.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Jan. 4, 1890; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 3p. Draft. Partly in pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Sends reply to Wallace's criticism on segregation.
  - Letter to the Treasurer of the Boston Society of Natural History, Jan. 14, 1890; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 2p. Draft. In pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Concerning payment for shells. Payment should be made to Mrs. Swett.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Jan. 21, 1890; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 2p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Printed: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.419-420.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, Feb. 15, 1890; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 8p. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning evolution, its definitions, and Wallace. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; p.420-422.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Gulick, March 14, 1890; B G96.r; 9-1/2x6; Swett, Charles E
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Gulick papers.) Has sent items for schools.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, April 10, 1890; B G96.r; 8x6-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 8p. Draft. Partly in pencil. (see Gulick papers.) Printed: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp:422-424.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, June 5, 1890; B G96.r; 8x5 and 7x6-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 12p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Printed: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.424-428.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, July 12, 1890; B G96.r; 7x4-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 12p. (see J.T.Gulick Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning evolution. Refers to Wallace, Darwin, etc. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; p.429-432.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, July 14, 1890; B G96.r; 6x4; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 2p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning terms for articles on evolution.
  - Letter to J[ohn T.] Gulick, Osaka, Japan, July 16, 1890; B G96.r; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S.with initials on postal card. 1p. and add. (see J.T.Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning evolution. Printed: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.432-433.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, July 19, 1890; B G96.r; 10x8; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 4p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning evolution and terminology for special parts of it. Refers to Wallace. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.433-435.
  - Letter to [John T.] Gulick, July 26, 1890; B G96.r; 6x4; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894
    A.L.S. 2p. (see J.T. Gulick. Correspondence with Romanes.) Concerning his controversy with Wallace and his desire to use Gulick's studies. Printed in part: A.Gulick. Evolutionist and missionary...; pp.435-436.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Aug. 27, 1890; B G96.r; 8x5; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923
    Osaka, A.L.S. 7p. Draft. (see Gulick papers.) Printed in part: Gulick. Evolutionist and Missionary; pp.436-438.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Sept. 16, 1890; B G96.r; 7x6-1/2; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923